Educational Technology Services Records UA245
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Great Courses, 2014 -- 2017; UA245.001; 626 Digital Object(s); 1 Web sites
  - Philosophy 167: Class 11 - Part 10 - Cassini's Effort to Rebuild Observational Astronomy: Picard's Expedition to Hven, and Richer's Expedition to Cayenne., 2014-11-18; gc.phil167.126
    Synopsis: Cassini set out to analyze Kepler's mechanics starting with new accurate observations, which takes 80 years. Opening line: "Once Cassini was there, remember, he had already decided in Bologna that Astronomy had to be built from the ground up." Duration: 14:09 minutes. Segment: Class 11, Part 10.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 11 - Part 11 - Correcting Chromatic Aberration: Newton and the Refraction Indices of Different Colors., 2014-11-18; gc.phil167.127
    Synopsis: In 1672, Newton published an explanation of chromatic aberration, and a new telescope design (the first reflecting telescope) which does not have chromatic aberration. Opening line: "It's in 1672, while Roche is down in Cayenne, that Newton publishes his first paper." Duration: 4:38 minutes. Segment: Class 11, Part 11.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 11 - Part 12 - The Eclipses of Io: Cassini and the Speed of Light., 2014-11-18; gc.phil167.128
    Synopsis: Observations of eclipses of Io caused the first speculation that planetary observations must be corrected for a measurable speed of light. Cassini resisted this idea for a long time. Opening line: "The tables were saying the eclipse should happen at a certain time, and the kind of error was eight minutes in time." Duration: 5:42 minutes. Segment: Class 11, Part 12.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 11 - Part 13 - Observational Astronomy in England: the Greenwich Observatory, Flamsteed's Research, and the Professionalization of the Scientific Community., 2014-11-18; gc.phil167.129
    Synopsis: John Flamsteed, the first royal astronomer of England, founded the Greenwich Observatory. Flamsteed used the observatory to create a new star catalog, replacing Tycho's. Opening line: "Now England doesn't have a Royal Observatory and France not only has one, they're sending expeditions out." Duration: 9:34 minutes. Segment: Class 11, Part 13.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 11 - Part 14 - Pressing Issues in Astronomy in 1679: Seven Ways of Calculating Planetary Orbits, and Ten Open Questions., 2014-11-18; gc.phil167.130
    Synopsis: Summarizes the status of astronomy in 1679, and the top ten unanswered questions of the time. Opening line: "All right, cuz what I wanna look at now is where astronomy stood, I'll finish tonight with this, where astronomy stood in 1679." Duration: 12:24 minutes. Segment: Class 11, Part 14.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 11 - Part 15 - Hooke on Attractive Powers in Celestial Bodies: a Guess at Universal Gravity., 2014-11-18; gc.phil167.131
    Synopsis: In 1674, Hooke proposed a universal gravity which causes all celestial bodies to be attracted to each other. Hooke later accused Newton of stealing the idea from him. Opening line: "Meanwhile, we have Hooke sitting there in the royal society." Duration: 6:35 minutes. Segment: Class 11, Part 15.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 12 - Part 1 - Isaac Newton: a Biography, 1642-1676., 2014-11-25; gc.phil167.132
    Synopsis: A brief biography of Isaac Newton from 1642 to 1676. Opening line: "This is the last class until very near the end of the next semester where I have this broad focus instead of looking almost proposition by proposition." Duration: 17:07 minutes. Segment: Class 12, Part 1.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 12 - Part 2 - Isaac Newton: a Biography, 1676-1727., 2014-11-25; gc.phil167.133
    Synopsis: A brief biography of Isaac Newton from 1676 to 1727. Opening line: "So just continuing, he has an exchange with Lagnus over the calculus in the mid 1670s." Duration: 19:24 minutes. Segment: Class 12, Part 2.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 12 - Part 3 - The Early Mathematics: Newton's Work While at Trinity College., 2014-11-25; gc.phil167.134
    Synopsis: Newton's early work in mathematics while at Trinity College, Cambridge; includes his work in developing calculus; a mention of his personality. Opening line: "We have his college notebook when he was first doing math and work in optics." Duration: 8:00 minutes. Segment: Class 12, Part 3.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 12 - Part 4 - Newton's Development of the Calculus: Infinite Equations, A Treatise of the Method of Fluxions, and Curvature., 2014-11-25; gc.phil167.135
    Synopsis: Newton's further work in calculus; derivatives; infinte equations; method of fluxions; curves. Opening line: "This is the first tract on Calculus. It's called Resolving Problems By Motion." Duration: 15:00 minutes. Segment: Class 12, Part 4.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 12 - Part 5 - The Optics: an Experimentum Crucis, the Relationship between Hypotheses and Experimental Results, and Newton's Wish for a Natural Science Supported by the Greatest Evidence., 2014-11-25; gc.phil167.136
    Synopsis: Newton's work in optics, including how to find imperfections; his first paper on light and colors; the experiment of the cross. Opening line: "This is from the same little notebook. This page is describing how to grind lenses." Duration: 16:10 minutes. Segment: Class 12, Part 5.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 12 - Part 6 - A Proposed Interpretation of How Newton Thought: Solving Problems, and then Asking Questions that Went Beyond Them., 2014-11-25; gc.phil167.137
    Synopsis: Discusses Newton's capacity to concentrate on a problem for a substantial length and very effectively. Opening line: "Let me say a couple things about now Newton and my picture of him, then we will look the rest of the class at the specific readings for today." Duration: 5:54 minutes. Segment: Class 12, Part 6.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 12 - Part 7 - Newton's Mechanics: Laws of Motion for a Theory of Impact, and Some Consequences., 2014-11-25; gc.phil167.138
    Synopsis: Introduces Newtonian mechanics and his interrest in angular momentum. Opening line: "Now, the one warning on this, the form in which I've put on assigned reading, the nine page document, is from Paravell's book, which you've already been reading for this week." Duration: 11:28 minutes. Segment: Class 12, Part 7.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 12 - Part 8 - Newton's Mechanics: a General Theory of Impact, and some Experimental Difficulties., 2014-11-25; gc.phil167.139
    Synopsis: Continues with Newtonian mechanics and his interrest in impact; mentions Newton's Third Law of Motion. Opening line: " Duration: 6:20 minutes. Segment: Class 12, Part 8.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 12 - Part 9 - Newton on Circular Motion: the Solution for Uniform Circular Motion, and the Inverse-Square Tendency of the Planets to Recede from the Sun., 2014-11-25; gc.phil167.140
    Synopsis: Discusses Newton's work on circular motion and its implications. Opening line: "Next document, this is a two page document. I think I included the actual manuscript. It's in Latin." Duration: 10:13 minutes. Segment: Class 12, Part 9.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 12 - Part 10 - The Moon Test: Concluding that the Moon Isn't Influenced by Terrestrial Gravity., 2014-11-25; gc.phil167.141
    Synopsis: Introduces the Moon Test and discusses Newton's calculations for the force of gravity. Opening line: "Now Newton does something rather striking with it. The term has come to be known, and you'll hear it all the rest of this course and next semester, the Moon Test." Duration: 4:16 minutes. Segment: Class 12, Part 10.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 12 - Part 11 - Two Proposed Accounts of the Purpose of the Moon Test: to Establish Universal Gravity, and to Establish Copernicanism over Tychonism., 2014-11-25; gc.phil167.142
    Synopsis: Continues discussing the Moon Test and Newton's calculations for the force of gravity. Opening line: "Now, what's he doing here? He's already figured out, three halves power rule, inverse square, given his solution for the circle." Duration: 12:30 minutes. Segment: Class 12, Part 11.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 12 - Part 12 - Motion Along a Cycloid: Newton on the Isochronism, and the Law, of Cycloidal Pendulums., 2014-11-25; gc.phil167.143
    Synopsis: Reviews Newton's work on motion long a cycloid; mentions Christopher Wren's work on the rectification problem for the cycloid; continues with Newton's work on vibrations. Opening line: "This is a letter from Newton to Oldenburg after he received the complimentary copy of Horologium Oscillatorium. " Duration: 8:00 minutes. Segment: Class 12, Part 12.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 12 - Part 13 - De Gravitatione et Aequipondio Fluidorum: a Reductio of Descartes' Theory of Motion., 2014-11-25; gc.phil167.144
    Synopsis: Review's Newton's De Gravitatione et Aequipondio Fluidorum; discuses Newton's definition of place, and then uses it to disprove Descartes. Opening line: "There's a manuscript we don't know how to date. It's called On gravity and the of Fluids." Duration: 6:32 minutes. Segment: Class 12, Part 13.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 1 - Newton-Hooke Correspondence: a Proposed Method for Detecting the Earth's Rotation, and Ideas for Analyzing Curvilinear Motion., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.145
    Synopsis: Letters between Hooke and Newton discuss directly measuring the rotation of the Earth, and measuring curved motion. Opening line: "And then Descartes' Principia which he, in spite of the influence it had on him, he really did not like the book very much at all." Duration: 22:51 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 1.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 2 - Newton-Hooke Correspondence: Hooke's Proposal of Using Forces Towards a Single Point., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.146
    Synopsis: Letters between Hooke and Newton discuss an attractive force pulling toward a single point, resulting in curvilinear motion. Opening line: "What I do want to show you, though, is what we, I think almost all of us who've worried about this, feel that Hooke contributed with this." Duration: 7:03 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 2.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 3 - Newton-Flamsteed Correspondence: Flamsteed's Proposed Account of Cometary Motion, and Newton's Response., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.147
    Synopsis: Letters between Flamsteed and Newton suggest that two comets were actually just one comet headed toward the sun and then away from the sun. Opening line: "Well, there's a comet that shows up going from north to south." Duration: 13:11 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 3.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 4 - Further Newton-Flamsteed Correspondence Concerning the 1680/1681 Comet: Flamsteed's Calculations of the Comet's Trajectory, and Newton's Response., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.148
    Synopsis: Flamsteed sent calculations of the two comets' trajectories to Newton, trying to prove they were the same orbit. Opening line: "So Flamsteed gets this letter, defends himself at length." Duration: 3:58 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 4.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 5 - Transitioning Towards Universal Gravity: Newton's Evolving Thought on Cometary Motion., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.149
    Synopsis: Newton initially dismissed the idea that comets could both approach and recede from the Sun, but later changed his mind. Opening line: "We have one further document. This is from Rupners paper of year 2000." Duration: 6:31 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 5.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 6 - Priority Dispute Over Inverse Square: the Conflict Between Newton and Hooke, and the Incipience of De Motu., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.150
    Synopsis: A dispute started over whether Hooke or Newton had first invented the inverse square law of force in orbital mechanics. Newton nearly stopped working on the project, but finally sent Halley a subsequently lost document believed to be titled De Motu. Opening line: "This story has become legendary. Many people have embellished it. What's fascinating about it is we have exactly one source of evidence about what happened." Duration: 7:45 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 6.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 7 - Generalizing Uniform Circular Motion: Hooke's Proposal Concerning Centripetal Forces, and Theorem 1 of De Motu., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.151
    Synopsis: Newton extended his inverse square theory from uniform circular motion to non-circular motion. Opening line: "So Newton knows how to do uniform circular motion. And I'm going to do it the way Hooke did it. I mean, Hooke. The way Huygens did it." Duration: 10:59 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 7.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 8 - De Motu Corporum in Gyrum: Definitions, Hypotheses, and a Comparison with Horologium Oscillatorium., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.152
    Synopsis: Summarizes the definitions and basic hypotheses of De Motu. Opening line: "All right, let me jump into Day Mo two. I'm not gonna go through it text by text. You can read it on your own." Duration: 11:37 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 8.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 9 - De Motu Corporum in Gyrum: Problem 1 and Problem 2., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.153
    Synopsis: Further mathematical analysis of De Motu. Opening line: "Newton now does three problems, the first problem looks really weird and I trust most of you, if you read with any care, thought why in the world is he doing this?" Duration: 12:12 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 9.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 10 - De Motu Corporum in Gyrum: Problem 3., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.154
    Synopsis: Further mathematical analysis of De Motu. Opening line: "This is for the Keplerian ellipse. So it's the same ellipse now, but we are sweeping out equal areas and equal times about a focus not about a center." Duration: 6:39 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 10.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 11 - The Original, Handwritten De Motu: Replacing 'Gravitatis' with 'Vis Centripetae'., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.155
    Synopsis: Newton switched from using the term 'gravitas' to the term 'vis centripeta', or centripetal force. Opening line: "This the actual document in facsimile. You can see the scratched out first hypothesis and replace." Duration: 4:56 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 11.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 12 - A Controversial Scholium in De Motu: Deriving the Ellipse from the Inverse Square., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.156
    Synopsis: Newton derived elliptical motion from his inverse square centripetal force. Opening line: "Problem three. A body orbits an ellipse. There is required to find the law of centrifugal force tending to a focus of the ellipse." Duration: 4:44 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 12.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 13 - De Motu Corporum in Gyrum: Theorem 4, Problem 4, and Two Key Scholia., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.157
    Synopsis: Further mathematical analysis of De Motu. Opening line: "Theorem for supposing that centripetal force be reciprocally proportional to the square root of the distance from the center." Duration: 12:30 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 13.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 14 - De Motu Corporum in Gyrum: Problem 5, and Trajectories Under Inverse-Square and Uniform Gravity., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.158
    Synopsis: Newton derived ballistic trajectories under uniform gravity with no air resistance. Opening line: "We've done everything we need to for this case of inverse square except direct vertical fall." Duration: 5:08 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 14.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 15 - De Motu Corporum in Gyrum: Problems 6 and 7, and Motion Under Resistance., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.159
    Synopsis: Newton then derived trajectories in the presence of air resistance. Opening line: "What he goes on to do in the last problems and I don't want to keep you too long, so I'm going to be very sketchy here." Duration: 6:59 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 15.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 13 - Part 16 - The Principal Accomplishments of De Motu: Keplerian Motion, Galilean Motion, and the Connection Between Mathematical Results and the Actual World., 2014-12-02; gc.phil167.160
    Synopsis: Summarizes the principles from Newtons De Motu. Opening line: "So we've got a series of results. I'm gonna state them fairly carefully now." Duration: 2:51 minutes. Segment: Class 13, Part 16.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 14 - Part 1 - A Summary of De Motu Corporum in Gyrum: Principal Results, and the Loose Ends that Led to the Principia., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.161
    Synopsis: Summarizes the main principles from De Motu, and points out three places where De Motu does not adequately justify conclusions. Opening line: "You've seen this slide before, when we reviewed astronomy between 16 between Descartes and Newton." Duration: 9:31 minutes. Segment: Class 14, Part 1.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 14 - Part 2 - De Motu Sphaericorum Corporum in Fluidis: a New Version of De Motu Corporum in Gyrum, and Five Laws., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.162
    Synopsis: Describes a second version of De Motu, emphasizing the changes between the two. Opening line: "All right, this is a document you can see at the top, the title. So this document is written in the hand of Humphrey Newton, his amanuensis at the time, with Isaac going in and making the changes, and the principle change on this page, the change that stands out, is he's got hypothesis one, hypothesis two, hypothesis three, hypothesis four all crossed out to the word law lex." Duration: 11:03 minutes. Segment: Class 14, Part 2.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 14 - Part 3 - Lemma 2: a Proof (from the New Laws in Fluidis), in the General Case, that Distance is Proportional to Time Squared., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.163
    Synopsis: A mathematical proof that distance covered under uniform acceleration is proportional to the square of the time. Opening line: "So, this proof is worth looking at. One of you, Issac challenged it last time, how it's even legitimate." Duration: 5:30 minutes. Segment: Class 14, Part 3.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 14 - Part 4 - The Copernican Scholium: Inordinate Complexity in the Actual Planetary Motions, and the Difficulty of Determining Correct Keplerian Orbits., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.164
    Synopsis: The center of gravity is affected by all the planets, so orbits are far more complex than simple ellipses, and are never repeated. Opening line: "Next is a long paragraph added to the scholium after theorem four. Theorem four is the three halves power rule for ellipses." Duration: 16:13 minutes. Segment: Class 14, Part 4.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 14 - Part 5 - The Copernican Scholium: a Proof of the Inordinate Complexity, Without the Notion of Universal Gravity., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.165
    Synopsis: Outlines a proof of the complexity of orbits, by looking at combining centers of gravity. Opening line: "What's the proof? Okay, what's the principle of center of gravity? Well, it's a balance." Duration: 7:25 minutes. Segment: Class 14, Part 5.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 14 - Part 6 - A Second New Scholium in Fluidis: Problems 4 and 5, and the Moon Test Revisited., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.166
    Synopsis: Newton discusses motion through a fluid, concluding that the ether that the planets move through has no resistance. He also concludes that the Moon's orbit proves the Earth's centripetal force decreases as the inverse square of distance. Opening line: "All right, the other thing that's added, there's a diagram changed in problem five. It's interesting, the diagram changed but the words did not. So I don't know what he had in mind when he changed the diagram." Duration: 11:37 minutes. Segment: Class 14, Part 6.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 14 - Part 7 - Newton-Flamsteed Correspondence: Flamsteed on the Puzzlingly Regular Motions of the Jovian Moons, and Newton on the Possible Interaction Between Jupiter and Saturn., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.167
    Synopsis: Letters between Flamsteed and Newton show that the orbits of Jupiters moons follow the three halves power law of Kepler, if you account for the speed of light as measured by Romer. They also speculate on gravitational interaction between Jupiter and Saturn. Opening line: "All right, what happens is, Newton starts a correspondence sometime in December of 1684 with Flamsteed." Duration: 11:29 minutes. Segment: Class 14, Part 7.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 14 - Part 8 - Newton-Flamsteed Correspondence: Flamsteed on the Lack of Observed Interaction Between Jupiter and Saturn, and Newton's Concern with Jupiter's Discrepancy from the 3/2 Power Rule., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.168
    Synopsis: In letters, Flamsteed doubts interaction between Jupiter and Saturn, and Newton talks about the small affect that Jupiter has on the motion of the Sun. Opening line: "All right, here's Flamsteed's answer, which will indeed answer Corey's question." Duration: 11:35 minutes. Segment: Class 14, Part 8.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 14 - Part 9 - Further Revisions to De Motu: Select Definitions in De Motu Corporum in Mediis Regulariter Cedentibus., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.169
    Synopsis: Summarizes the changes in yet another version of De Motu. Opening line: "This is a document, if it's a fragment. He's changed the title again on the motion of bodies in regularly yielding media." Duration: 13:33 minutes. Segment: Class 14, Part 9.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 14 - Part 10 - Further Revisions to De Motu: Select Laws in Cedentibus, and the Notion of Mass., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.170
    Synopsis: Newton introduces the concept of mass independent of discussion of gravity. Opening line: "Now the, oh, the laws. What is new here is, and this is again Heravel's translation, because law four has the relative motion of bodies enclosed as a given space." Duration: 9:19 minutes. Segment: Class 14, Part 10.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 14 - Part 11 - How Newton Discovered the Law of Gravity: the Accepted View, and a Variant of It as Presented in De Motu Corporum, Liber Secundus., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.171
    Synopsis: Discusses how Newton may have discovered the Law of Gravity. Opening line: "But now we've got something very significant because now we can actually see the principle that's called the Law of Gravity almost staring us in the face." Duration: 29:46 minutes. Segment: Class 14, Part 11.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 14 - Part 12 - Universal Gravity: a Sequence of Increasingly Implausible Claims., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.172
    Synopsis: Newton proposes universal gravity, acting between all bodies proportional to their masses and inversely to the square of their distance. Opening line: "What's happened here is we've seen a sequence of proposals. There are 11 stages of this that form the theory of universal gravity that Newton's gonna defend in the Principia." Duration: 3:44 minutes. Segment: Class 14, Part 12.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 14 - Part 13 - A Summary of the Progression to Newton's Principia: Milestones, Questions Raised, and Three Revolutions in Evidence., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.173
    Synopsis: Summarizes the scientific advances which led up to Newton's Law of Gravity, and the remaining questions to be resolved in Principia. Opening line: "So to end the course, five minutes, it's a series of three comments." Duration: 6:08 minutes. Segment: Class 14, Part 13.
  - Slides to Philosophy 167: Class 4 -- Kepler's Planetary System and the Rudolphine Tables -- Part 8., 2014-09-23; gc.phil167.423
    Generally corresponds to the video segment: Class 4, Part 8.
  - Slides to Philosophy 167: Class 1 -- Overview of the Course;Ptolemaic Astronomy -- Complete., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.375
    Section: Class 1, Complete.
  - Slides to Philosophy 167: Class 1 -- Overview of the Course;Ptolemaic Astronomy -- Part 1., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.376
    Generally corresponds to the video segment: Class 1, Part 1.
  - Slides to Philosophy 167: Class 1 -- Overview of the Course;Ptolemaic Astronomy -- Part 2., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.377